[intro music plays]
Hi, and welcome to the July
edition of According to Pete.
Today, we're gonna talk about current sensing
why you wanna do it
how you gonna do it
and at the end I'm gonna run you
through calibration
of one of our current sensors that
we have available.
So the reason why we do current
sensing is because
we, um, we we expect
a current to change in a certain
part of a circuit
or we need to make operational decisions
based on a what a circuit is doing
or we're afraid that something
is going to burn
(this is usually my case).
I'm afraid something's going to burn
and I wanna know if the
current is going up
in a certain section so
I can shut it off.
so there's a couple of different
ways to, uh,
to sense current in a circuit.
This, using Ohm's law
okay so suppose you got
something sitting out here
that is, uh,  going to have
a varying in current you need to
know what it's going to do
right? Okay. So one method of
sensing current is to actually place
a resistance in series with your load
and ideally it's a very
small resistance, right?
And I'll explain that in a sec.
So typically you something like a
0.1 ohm resistor
and so as current changes in this thing
there is a really small little signal
that generates over this resistor
Okay. Really small,
kinda hard to read
so what you typically do
is you take this to an
instrumentation amplifier
so I can op-amp and get a signal
in here
and another one there
nuh neh
and, um, and actually, I've
just cut to the chase
there's a few parts that do exactly this
the INA169
and the reason it's a cool little part
is because when you set up
an instrumentation amplifier like this
you have a couple
resistances here, you needed
a little driver circuit
and goes to load and you
measure something else
the cool thing about this is that
if you don't have a part
that's got all these things
on a single die
you end up with tolerances
that are really wiggy
but the, the guy in a 169
actually takes care
of this for you
it's kind of a cool part.
the problem with this
is that if you're sensing
a really large current
this resistor will create a much
larger voltage than
you might wanna have
between your load and ground
like for example 0.1 Ohm
resistor will generate
you know, at 10 Amps it'll
generate a Volt of noise
A lotta times that's not acceptable
OK, now something also cool and
I'll  write this down
INA169
another cool thing about this part is
it's a high side sensor
what that means is that
you don't haveto put
the resistor down here
on the low side
you can put it up here
on the high side.
Now that's cool and all,
problem is this is still a
series circuit, you're still going to
introduce noise to your load
Okay. But, since its a high-side sensor
what you can do
is you can put it
before your VREG
voltage regulator. Okay, voltage
regulators designed
to take that noise out
so you can still sense what's
going on in your circuit
without actually introducing
a whole bunch of noise
pretty cool, huh?
The other method of
doing this is, uh,
by Hall Effect.
Basically any conductor that has
a current going through it
makes a magnetic field, right?
and so we've got a sensor
that can sense that and I'll tell you
how much the magnetic fields doing
And blah blah blah blah.
We sell a part called the ACS712
and it is a Hall effect current sensor
The first cool thing
grab marker
where Ohm's Law related parts like
the INA169 are concerned
they're using a resistance ...
like ... .1 Ohm
which is a small resistance but
like I was saying before
at 10 amps is generating
a volt of noise
okay, and there's ways around it
this guy, comparatively, its in-line
resistance
is on the order of 1.2 milli Ohms
so in like two orders of
magnitude less
So the upshot of that
is you can use it on the low side
and it's not gonna generate
that much noise to your load, okay?
Second thing, the current path
through this device
is completely isolated
from the sensing circuit
Right? So what that means
is you can also use it
on the high side
the reason you can't do, or why
high side sensing is difficult
is because you have this
common mode voltage
that is so different from the
supply voltage of the sensor
Right? and the INA169 allows
you to do this.
It'll allow like sixty votes of higher
voltage from its supply voltage
and won't go wonky. Okay.
This thing has an isolated
current path, so
you can use it on the low side,
you can use high side
it doesn't matter. You don't have
to use it in front of a regulator.
You can put this thing
pretty much anywhere.
The third thing about this
that's cool
at zero current through this
it will give you and output that is
VCC over two. Right?
Half of your supply voltage.
Right? So externally you're
powering this thing from 5 Volts
and it's got a ground, and then
a sense voltage over here
so if your power
in this thing with 5 volts
it'll give you an output of
two and a half Volts
when there's no current going through it
what does that mean?
That means it'll do
negative current as well
as positive current
so this part, the one,
the version that we sell
is the five Amp version it comes
in a few different versions
The 5 Amp version has,
and I got in my notes here
deflection of 185 milli Volts
at the output per Amp
that goes through this thing.
Now that's not
what I would call really great
resolution.
A lot of currents that we deal with here
are small currents. Right?
We make a board
that's got this part this part
plus a buffer amplifier with
some gain.
you can set the gain, and you
can set the reference voltage
and it works out pretty cool
that's SKU SEN08883
Point I wanna make
whether you using this thing
or you're using in the INA169
or other derivative
you always want to
calibrate these things, right?
because, um, there are tolerances
there is some drift
you might have to deal with
there's probably some noise you
have to deal with
and I'll talk about that in a sec
so always wanna go through some
kinda calibration with these
you gotta know how much current
you're getting per
millivolt of deflection.
Here we are again
I've got this hooked up
and this was my ADC example
from a couple months ago
the code is, oh,
I altered the code a little bit to
average out some of these readings.
This thing can be noisy
so you are going to have to do a
little bit of averaging in code
makes it a lot easier to read something
and I've got this set up from
a power supply
and I've got it limited over there to
about 100 ish milliamps
and I got my meter here
I'm using this as my calibration
standard
HAH! HAH! HAH!
I don't think this has ever been
calibrated since it left the factory
I've got my five Volt supply,
I've got ground
I got my sense line going to my ADC value
and it's spitting out here
this is the current
going through the meter coming
from my power supply over there
first thing you do set your reference
current to zero.
Once you know that it's
zero current, 0 current
you set the reference on this guy
and I apologize this being upside
down from where you're looking
There's 2 adjustments on this.
There's two pots
one says V ref one says gain
first thing you wanna to do is you
wanna set the V ref pot
and basically just set this assuming
you've got a set up like this
or maybe you're reading it
with a voltmeter
you just wanna set it to the point
where you wanna start reading from so if
So if you wanna do
positive and negative current possibly
you'd set it for a halfway value
of your ADC
in this case were
running on a 10-bit ADC
on the breadboard
and so it's somewhere
around 512 or thereabouts
okay? That we get positive
and negative deflection
so you set that,
and I sent this earlier
and it's right about 515, Eh
course enough,
doesn't have to be exact
you also want to take note
of the value, right
so mark mark this down
and it's a little a little noisy
right? so you gotta kinda look at it
and go hmm, 530 ish or so
right that value down
then what you do you set
your current to the max value
that you wanna read
so if for example
you expect a circuit to be drawing
fifty milliamps
you might set your max current
on your current reference to
a hundred milliamps. Okay?
So you can see some
some deflection there.
Hook that guy up
and my reference here
says I'm running about
102 milliamps
so that's pretty close, right?
take note of that value then you set
the gain pot over here
this guy
to about as much deflection
as you want to read
or max deflection, right.
So if you're going from
500 to whatever and
I'll tell you something
the op-amp buffer out here on
this board is an inverting opamp
so if you have positive going current
it's going to give you a
negative going pulse
from your reference of
hundred-and-some ADC value.
Okay? So you adjust the gain pot
until you get, you know, a fairly
decent number that you can read
easily for your maximum
current deflection
That make sense?
So previously I adjusted this thing
and I'm getting about
three... fifty... three four
in there someplace. Okay? So you
take note of that value
then what you do is you set your
reference current to 0 again
so you disconnect it and you
double check that your VREF
ADC value is still steady. If it's not,
you gotta go back and do it again
um, and sometimes you know
your power supply can drift
[hesitant moaning]
we're ballparking here, come on.
Um,  I'm so you gotta watch,
that but this is just to verify
that you did it right, sort of sanity
check OK everything's still the same
we can move on now.
Then you have your maximum and
minimum current being zero
and a 102 milliamps and you have
uh, your ADC, Right. So I'm
what am i doing? I'm I'm defining
a line and it's a linear relationship
so I have I have my points and I
have my slope and I'm, yeah,
basically I'm just figure out
the equation for a line
Right? And so a earlier I had set this up
and I came out with a resolution
of about
0.56 milliamps per ADC division. Okay?
So , you know, roughly about 500 microamps
not too bad and then once you
have that number
you just apply it in your code.
It's that simple.
I will warn you that's
this, this is not, I mean we're we're
talking about
millivolts worth of deflection here.
Okay? That's in the noise. So you're
gonna have to, like, for example
my, my code that I'm running on this thing
I'm averaging it quite heavily.
I mean I'm, I'm, averaging a
thousand ADC reads
um, and I'm getting updates roughly
about every hundred milliseconds
which is not too bad.
Will it do a higher frequency?
Yes it'll do higher frequency
but you're gonna have to, you know,
condition that in code
or maybe you wanna to put like
another cap on the output
of the op amp but
off the top of my head I can't
remember if the OPA344
which is the op amp in that, uh
how steady it is for how much value
output capacitance.
You might wanna check that.
I don't tell you anything that's a lie.
Ohh, I've got current! That's
low current sensor board.
I definitely don't want to steer you
away from the ah, ah
the Ohm's Law ones that use the
resistors we do sell a few those
you know they they are good parts,
um, but you know
they have their application just like
this one has application
and your mileage may vary.
Think about what you want and
then make a selection that's cool.
Keep the questions and comments
coming
and put them in the comments section
down yar or you can email them to
feedback@sparkfun.com with
"According to Pete" in the subject
line and we will check em out and
get them in the queue
Until next month, thanks for
watching. See ya.
Make love to the camera.
[Pete] Are we going?
[Person in background] Yah.
[music plays]