Hi
and welcome to the November edition of
According to Pete
Today we're gonna cover
uh,transistor biasing configurations
which is probably kind of a wacky thing.
I had originally thought that, uh,
hey I'm gonna do MOSFET biasing circuits that'll be cool
and then I figured out I don't know anything
about MOSFET biasing circuits.
Yet.
But instead I'm gonna back up a little bit
and do transistor biasing
and I thought
great, I can cover
, uh, common base
and common collector and
common emitter in one big...
No you can't do this
I fear that's insanity
so today I'm going to cover
uh, common base configuration
which honestly is
very rarely used, and common
emitter configuration which is
more often use but not as much
as the third one that we're gonna
do later, called common emitter
so for the, uh, the case
of, uh, of for for
for the sake of argument
for the sake of our examples
we're going to talk about standard
small-signal NPN transistor
remember this guy, points to
the N material, so NPN
Imagine this to be
your standard garden variety
2N3904, we all know 'em,
we all love 'em
if you will recall,
little bit a review,
you get a small current
going from base
to emitter and that gives you a
large current
[lip buzzing sound]
that goes from
emitter or collector to emitter.
Okay?
So, the proportion, there's a proportion
for how big this current is to
the how big this current is
and that is called, you look on a datasheet
hfe
or Beta, Okay?
and that number for to 2N3904
is something on the order of
100 to 300
depending on where you have the transistor biased
The, the idea is like, so
one micro amp through the base emitter junction
will give you, um, what?
10 milliamps at a factor of a hundred
going from collector to emitter the
first thing you got to do before
before anything else can happen you
gotta turn the transistor on
you get a small current going through here
you get a large current going
through here. Right?
Which means setting it up with a
DC quiescent state, right?
The reason we want to use
this thing is to pass an AC signal
could be audio,
could be RF,
could be a sensor,
could be a lot of different things.
In general, what you do, is you set up
this voltage divider, R1 and R2
so that you have
a known voltage here which for the
sake of argument will just say is
Vd+  over 2 which it's not
necessarily ever going to be
but it's good for for starting someplace, right?
Now, um, for this being a 2N3904
you can expect, right, this is a diode.
Right? We talked about that in the previous
You don't remember some stuff, go
back to the transistors episode
that was way long ago and
review some of this
Okay? This is a diode, and you
gotta turn guy this on
and you can assume, "assume"
that this is about
0.6 volts dropped from here to here.
So if you know you've got
V-plus over two, half of VCC,
then you know
you would know that you've
got 0.6 volts
less than that here.
If V+ was 10 volts
(which you totally cannot read)
10 Volts, and then that makes this
5 Volts and that makes this
4.4 Volts. Okay? 4.4 Volts.
You set up your emitter collector
current
with that resistor, alright?
You know you got 4.4 Volts here
and in the process of designing the
circuit and we'll get the some of that
be cool,
you calculate this value
to give you your current through
emitter to collector
using Ohms Law, okay?
So if I wanted 5 milliamps going
through here I would say
okay 4.4 both divided by 5 milliamps is
X Ohms, and I would set that value to be
X Ohms, and then these are just a
resistor divider
but their values can become critical
depending on the application
and this will become clearer as I go.
This guy
is typically used for setting up
a , um, an operating point
or limiting current through this thing
and that'll become clearer...
I keep saying that, right?
General concepts right now.
First thing you wanna do is
turn it on with regard to DC,
and this is what we're doing,
we setup our divider
we figure out our voltage here,
we figure out how much current is here
and these are all going to be iterative
When you're working with stuff like this
this is not an exact science. Alright
This is an iterative process.  Um,
If you've been watching my shows
for all this time and you think
that electronics is a precise thing
you've been not
paying attention brother or sister
Um, this is, this is iterative
it-er-a-tive
and always plan for it to be
because it's never gonna come out
just perfect.
Now the first configuration
I'm gonna talk about is called
common base
Um, and I start with this on because
it's the the "low-key one?"
It's probably not low key at all,
but it's the one that is,
uh, least commonly used,
so call it uncommon base.
you put an input on the emitter
which is unusual, and you take your
output from the collector
which is not unusual.
The input impedance, right,
so the amount of current that
this circuit is gonna try to draw
off of the source, it'll try to draw
all of the current.
the input impedances are very low.
Okay? Um, like on the order of
less than 10 Ohms typically.
and the output impedance is rather high
I'm in fact, it is said that the source
the source impedance, [stumbling]
or the source current, uh,
is carried all the way to the output,
and in fact your Z out is approximated by R source
whatever this's internal resistance is, um,
divided by the beta of the transistor.
So it's not a great thing, its current
gain is a little bit less than 1
its voltage gain can be quite high.
Problem is, the voltage gain is
difficult to calculate
and is highly dependent on the thermal voltage
of the device. Oh my gosh!
Go look up Boltzmann constant.
The gain is unpredictable,
the current gain is terrible,
and the input impedance, sucks.
So for that reason this configuration is generally relegated to things
like the front end of a radio, were you're trying to match
the impedance of an antenna.
This is terrible at low frequencies and the reason is because
because the input impedance is only a few Ohms
now remember this reef, this this equation:
1/(2*pi*R*C),
that, is, f, that's your corner frequency
for this input impedance and that
capacitor
so you gonna try to calculate that
capacitor based on that.
and a lower the frequency is
and the lower that resistance is
the more awful that cap is going to become.
So at low frequencies this thing is
just about completely unworkable
what I know, is that this circuit is
used for voltage gain.
Okay?
So I'm going to have a large swing
on the output which is at the collector
now, the first thing, is I go "Ahh!"
my supply voltage is 10 Volts,
so I want my quiescent operating
point of my output
to be at half at that, Okay? So I
know this is going to be 5 Volts
not even close to writing, hurray.
5 Volts. Okay, that's a choice,
that is
that is something, I want
my output to be able to swing
up to 10 and down to 0 as cleanly as possible so I set that there.
I know that this will this has to
be less than that
I don't know how much but, mmmm
Since I've never set one of these up I took a guess, Right?
I just wanna see where it ends up
So I set this value
to 2 Volts. I also know
that the input impedance is is or the inputs, the R in if you will
is going to be the thermal voltage divided by the...
I'll just write it down.
Rin (I hope you can read this a little bit)
equals Vt over Ie,
Ie is the emitter current
Okay? Vt is the thermal voltage and if you look this up
it is highly dependent on the temperature of the junction.
Okay? At room temperature the thermal voltage
is about 20... s... Wow does this suck!
26 millivolt. Okay? It's a small number.
If I just choose a value and for the sake of my example
I just chose a value, because I wanted to see what would come out
and I chose it to be 5 milliamp
with that value at room temperature
Rin comes out to be 5.2 Ohms.
Ha ha, that's nuts. More importantly
um, with my choice of that, my choice of 2 Volts
I know that 2 Volts divided by 5 milliamps is going to be 400 Ohms
for the value of a Re, R emitter
Now I also know that since I've chosen my quiescent points
to be at 5 Volts till I get maximum
upswing and maximum downswing
at 5 milliamps I have a value of 1K
for my Rc, which is resistor collector
this is to collect a resistor, resistor collector, I collect resistors
so I got values for this, I got value for this, I know that's 2 Volts
and I assume that this point is going to be 2.6 Volts.
Okay? Because we know that the voltage drop across this
from base to emitter is about 0.6 Volts. Now that's not a guarantee
that's an assumption it could be anywhere from
0.55 up to 0.75, and it's gonna depend on device to device.
From there I just gotta set up my divider for 2.6 Volts.
How much current has to go through this divider?
that is a little bit of a critical question.
When you set these guys up
and this goes for any these configurations we're gonna talk about
you generally want your
your divider current, which goes neh, neh ,neh,
to be a factor of 10
more than the current that you know is going through here
Okay? So if I've chosen 5 milliamps to go through here
and I know the beta of the transistor
which is also variable, but if I assume it to be
100 for small signal device like this, that's not a bad assumption
I can assume that, you know, if I got 5 milliamps here
I've got 50 microamps that's going this way, okay?
so I want a factor of 10, so, like 500 microamps going here
Now for the sake of my example, I didn't do that,
I swamped the heck out of it
and I just said "yeah I make that 5 milliamps too,shure what the heck"
5 milliamps, and so it now it's just a matter calculating resistor values
Okay? So for R2 down here I got 520 Ohms
and for R1 up here I got 1480
now you're going to calculate all kinds values that are not particularly standard.
Okay? So you're gonna have to make the choice
am I going to create a resistor
am I going to make do with what I can get my hands on.
Let's talk about a how we expect it to work, right?
So if you've got an input here, and I always encourage
like, a mechanical understanding what you're actually looking at.
So you're putting in a signal at Vin.
Right? So there's an instantaneous
voltage that occurs at this point
because for that cap, signal, that that's a short, right?
so you can expect, you know,
signals going to appear there and that's not even going to be in the circuit
So, with that if your Vin
is going low, what's going to happen here?
its gonna pull this point low and since the base is stable
its gonna turn that sucker on, really hard, right?
so when this guy turns on much much harder
it becomes a smaller resistance, right?
so it's gonna bring this value down,
so the outputs gonna go down
Now when you send the input high, just the opposite
its gonna bring this point higher
and its gonna shut of the transistor because your base is held at 2.6 Volts. Right?
so this becomes a larger resistor, and so you're gonna have
a positive going signal.
so what this tells us is that your input and output are in phase.
my input impedance for my choice of emitter current is 5.2 Ohms.
that is not very good.
It may occur to the viewer that in fact the input impedance
is not just this but it is this and this. Right? Well, OK,
first thing, point out
these resistors are'nt even going to enter into the equation
and reason is because I that cap right there
because that's an AC ground, okay?
So these resistors it's not really very critical what their
values are necessarily, unless this is like,
you know depending on how much branch current you want
through here you increase their values
but they're not going to come into the input impedance equation
because that is single ground, okay?
this guy, this guy will also not come into it because
he is two orders of magnitude above what we're looking at
so that's not gonna come into the equation either
so it's basically going to be that.
Now I can improve that, right, if I chose this resistor value
right? still 2 Volts but if I chose the
chose this to not past 5 milliamps but to pass 1 milliamps
for example I could increase that
by a factor of five. Still not great but it's better.
the voltage gain of this circuit is not very easily predicted
and its highly dependent on the value of emitter current
the greater your emitter current
the greater voltage gain,
the lower your input impedance.
This is called the emitter follower,
or common collector.
the idea here is that you put a signal in on the base
and you take the output at the emitter
So the emitter follows the base.
The characteristics of this circuit are
a high, relatively speaking, a high Zin, input impedance,
and a relatively low output impedance.
So it's a current driver, okay?
now because this voltage follows this voltage
your voltage gain is going to be just slightly less than 1.
Now you notice
there is no resistor or collector resistor here
and that's to facilitate lots and lots of current going to your load,
ultimately. If you put a high going signal on the inputs
you know this point has to be within 0.6 Volts
of that, right, so if you put something in here
this is going to be 0.6 under it.
so you're gonna have a high going there
so your input and output are in phase, just like the common base
I assigned myself a value of VCC to be 9 Volts
because I don't want to make anything easy by making it 10 Volts again
if I know my output signal is here and I know
that I want it to be halfway between VCC and ground
then I know that this is 4.5 Volts.
Okay? I know that points going to be 4.5 Volts
and, because I know that, I know this point is gonna be 5.1 Volts
We want to choose a quiescent current
which is, you know,
the current that its gonna have running through it
with no input signal, and we want to choose it to be
sorta low. And the reason we wanna to be sorta low
is because we want this transistor to be able to source all of its
extra current through the load,
we don't want it going this way, we want it going that way
I chose this value, again, to be 5 milliamps.
So if I've got 5 milliamps going this way
and I know I've got 4.5 Volts here then I immediately know that
my value for Re, down there
is going to be 900 Ohms.
Now, choosing values for these guys same rule
as with the common base which is to say that
whatever your base emitter current is
you want your branch current here to be like a factor 10 above that
to swamp out the effects of that thing.
so if I've got 5 milliamps here and I assume a beta of about a hundred
then I've got 50 microamps going yay wise
50 microamps, and a factor 10 or that is 500 microamps.
but, me being me, I just chose a value
and I said it was 2 milliamps.
To set up 5.1 Volts at 2 milliamps, the numbers I got
were are 2250
no that's going to be really picky, 2250 Ohms for R2
and for R1 I got 1950 Ohms.
As I was saying before the input impedance
on this circuit, in general, is considered relatively high
To calculated how to completely what you're looking at
Right? A signal going here is going to be actually
this resistor R1 in parallel with R2
in parallel with ,um, beta...
beta times Re
For the sake of this example I assumed
a beta of 80. I don't know I did that, okay, I just did it
so what we're talking about is 1950
in parallel with 2250 in parallel with
I calculated it out 72 K becomes that resistor.
So when you add up all those in parallel
you get a whopping 1392 Ohms.
2 milliamps might not have been a very good choice.
a factor of 10 on that would bring me down like I said
to 500 microamps
which is much better in fact I recalculated
all that stuff and I ultimately got, you know, if you
if you assume this is 500 microamps these numbers change
to 7800 for that guy
and
and 10,200 for R2
and so your parallel input impedance
becomes about 40164
So about a factor of 3 better.
I can also drop my emitter current
this does not have to be 5 milliamps,
I can drop it to like 1 milliamps and I could get this number
up even more
The source, whatever's coming out here, I don't wanna tax it
too very much
so the higher input impedance I get the better that's gonna be
the other thing is that cap, right?
once again 1/(2*pi*R*C)
equals f.
The higher this number is
the lower that cap value can be and it's easier to achieve
a lower value than a high-value in a lot of cases.
My output impedance is approximated,
boy this is getting really nasty isn't it?
is approximated,
Zout is about R source over beta. Okay?
so whatever the output impedance of this guy is divide that by beta
and that's what you can assume outta here.
why would you use this circuit over an op amp or something else?
well you wouldn't necessarily.
The two circuits that I've shown you so far are not very interesting to me
The most interesting one
is going to come when we talk about common emitter, and
the reason you would use that one over an op amp,
that one gives you voltage gain and current gain
and the reason you would use that one over an opamp
is because op amps are optimized for linearity
whereas the transistor
you try to work really hard to make it linear
which sounds like a downside, but it isn't always a downside
because it allows you to really jack with your signal in
really interesting ways, okay?
You can add harmonics, you can do mixing
you can... it becomes kinda wacky,
and the three configurations that I'm showing you are really
only the tip of the iceberg
they're just enough the little bit into it
and then cut you loose so fly from the nest and see what you do
That's it for this time
admittedly the first to common base and common collector
are mildly interesting but it's more to illustrate
the process of setting up a bias on a circuit so you can use it like that
the transistor
keep the questions and comments coming,
check out the engineering group
@sfe_engineering on Twitter or check out
the Sparkfun proper at Sparkfun
wait you're looking the other way
at Sparkfun
send your questions and comments to
feedback@sparkfun.com with "According to Pete" in the subject line
or put them in the comments section below
Thanks for tuning in and I will see you next month
[background voice] Rant away
[Pete] I'm zoning out
[music plays]