[Intro Music]
Hello everyone. This is Robert with SparkFun Electronics,
and welcome to our into to robotics video.
In the past, we've typically only carried electronics
prototyping boards and things of that nature.
We really haven't carried all the components
you need to build your robot. Well, we are looking
to change that. We are vary proud to introduce the
Actobotics product line where we will be carrying
500 additional robotic components, strictly for robotics.
So, now you can have the electronics and
the robotic components all in one place
and you don't have to go shopping around for everything.
This is the first of the 9 part video series where we
explain all the different components that go
into building a robot. We're going to talk about
belts, pulleys, gears, bearings, and all the other
things that you'll need to know to build your
very own robotic creation.
Before we get into that let's first
talk about what is robotics.
[Transition Music]
Robots are electromechanical systems designed
to typically to help people with tedious repetitive
and sometimes dangerous tasks. Robots are
comprised of actuators, being motors or
servos; and sensors being user inputs or
electronic sensors. Robots are all around us.
From the dishwasher in our kitchen,
to the robot vacuum cleaners cleaning our floors.
We even have robots on Mars. Robots are
essential to manufacturing. With the use of
automated welders to build our cars,
to CNC machines to build our circuit boards. While robots
maybe useful, they're sometimes difficult to
design and build. There's motors,
there's sensors, there's computers,
and interfacing all these together is quite
a challenge crossing many disciplines.
Through this video series we are going to
try to give you some shortcuts in understanding
some of these different disciplines.
[Transition Music]
So, when building a robot there's a lot
of different parts and pieces you're going to
need. You're going to need anything from shafts,
to wheels, to gears, to motors... The one thing
we really like about Actobotics is all the parts
work together. They have common hole spacing.
They've event got 0.77 inch or 1.5 inch that
all the parts use so they easily mate together
and you can use these in any different
configuration and you don't have to worry about
re-drilling or tapping a hole; it all just works
together nicely. So, be sure to join us next
week for the next installment of the robotic
video series which will be angular motion.
We're going to be talking about: wheels,
barrings, shafts, and also all the different
types of motors that you could be using.
So, see you then!
[Outro Music]