[Intro Music]
Hello everyone! This is Robert with SparkFun Electronics,
and this is the second video of our robotic video series.
And today we are going to be talking about
angular motion. Angular motion can be as simple as
rotating a wheel to drive a robot, or rotating some
kind of leaver or arm, or even like spinning a
rotisserie chicken. There's a lot of different ways
that you can apply angular motion to your robotic
project.
[Transition Music]
Motors convert electricity into mechanical
power. They come in various shapes, sizes,
and configurations. Brush motors are the
workhorse of robotics in industry.
They have a very good torque response curve
with a wide RPM range. They're very simple
to control requiring only two leads to be connected
to a battery or power source. As the name would
suggest, they have brushes. These brushes
translate power to a ring called the commutator.
This commutator is essentially the controller
of a brush motor, supplying current to the
windings propelling the motor forward.
These brushes over time can wear out
and in some cases lead to inefficiencies
since they are made of carbon. This
is the same stuff resistors are made of.
Modern motors have solved this problem
by using precious metals or special
compounds. One thing to note is
servos are actually brush motors in disguise.
They have a little control loop inside that makes
them behave a little differently, but we'll get
into that later. Moving on to stepper motors,
these are typically found in CNC machines,
3D printers, and anything else that requires
high positioning accuracy. Stepper motors have
exceptional holding torque, at the expanse of
higher RPM. Stepper motors are not quite as
easy to control as compared to a DC brush motor.
They require an external driver which are inexpensive
and easy to come by. Now let's take a look
inside of a stepper motor. As you can see
the coils are stationary, and the magnet
assembly is actually what spins. This is different
from a brush motor, because it has no brushes.
What gives a stepper its name is these little
grooves here. These are little teeth that
redirect the magnetic fields to create a
much smaller, what's called, step distance.
And this is what gives the motor exceptional
holding torque. Moving on to brushless motors,
they're a little bit different then stepper
motors, but they share a lot of similarities.
Both are spinning magnets verses the coils
but brushless motors have a much larger,
what we would call, step distance. Where as
stepper motors usually have from 200 to 400
steps per revolution, brushless motors have
between 6 and 12. The advantages of this
are that they have a much higher operating
RPM, but the disadvantage is that they have
very low starting torque. They require very
specialized controllers to optimize for the
application of the user. With new controllers
coming out on the market, with the advent of
quad-copters and ground vehicles, brushless motors
are becoming more prevalent in robotics.
So, how do I choose the right motor for my
application? When I need things to be positioned
accurately, or have a high holding torque,
I look to the stepper motor. When I need things
to be very fast, I look to the brushless motor.
And for pretty much everything else, I look
to the DC brush motor. Now in future videos
we'll show how to take a brush motor
or a stepper motor and use it as a very precise
positioning system.
[Transition Music]
So let's talk about how to connect your
motors to the other various Actobotics components.
We've got four of the different motor mounts
here. These mounts can actually be found on the
website under robotics, mounts and hubs,
and motor mounts. There's a whole category
just for the motor mounts. First up we've got the
Motor Mount A which looks a little something
like that; we've got the Motor Mount D;
we've got the Clamp Mount; and we've got the
Clamping Swivel Mount. Let's start with the A.
The A is good for connecting to the outside of
channels like this. So first what we need to do
is line up holes with these two holes located
on the face of the motor. This should be the
same for standard or the precision motors.
I'm just going to use two screws. There you go.
Now you have a versatile mount that can mount
to the outside of the Actobotics channels.
So if we use a quarter inch screw, we can
easily thread that through and attach this.
So now we have a secure connection to the
motor. Well, what if we want to mount on the inside
open part of the channel? We will want to use the
motor mount D. This mounts very similar to this one, but
mounts inside the channel like this.
So it's always a good idea, before you put this
in the channel, to get the shaft coupler attached
to your output shaft, just so you don't have to
go reach inside and screw this later.
Shaft couplers are basically these little
metal tubes that have these set screws on
each side, and one shaft goes in on side,
one shaft goes in the other side,
and you clamp them down and you can transfer
the motion from the shaft of your motor to another
shaft, or you can even attach a wheel on the
other side. There's a lot of different types
of shaft couplers and they come in two bores.
The first bore is the size of the inner hole
size and the other bore is the size of the other
side. Now all we need to do is fit on our flange
bearing and the flange will keep it from going
inside the channel. There we go.
We're going to use a plastic
shaft spacer that will give a little bit of a
buffer between that and our hub clamp which
we will then attach like this. So now that we
have the hub on the end of here, we have a
0.77 inch hole pattern, that we can use to
attach any wheel that has a 0.77 inch hole
pattern, or with the use of an adapter we can
actually adapt it to a larger wheel, like this 1.5.
Two more motor mounting options we have are
this motor clamp and also this swivel clamp.
The motor mount is actually pretty simple,
and all we need to do is line it up with a
1.5 inch hole pattern, like so, slide the motor
in place, clamp down the set screw, and we've
got a really simple way to mount a motor.
The other benefit of this motor mount is that
since the motor can actually slide inside,
and the motor output shaft is offset, it acts
as an adjustment to adjust the motor
up and down, closer to what ever you are trying
to attach to. The swivel mount is very similar
to this one, except for it has a swiveling base.
This base connects to the channel in the same
way, but with the aid of this screw, it allows
you to adjust the orientation of the motor,
any which way you want. So these two together,
along with the rotation inside the channel,
gives you a very flexible motor mounting solution.
What if you have two shafts that are slightly
misaligned. This is an example of a helical
coupler. It just has these spiral cuts which
allows for angular misalignment. You might not
be able to line up the shafts like this,
but if you have any angular misalignment,
that's exactly why you would use a helical
coupler. A traditional shaft coupler is going
to be good for two shafts that are perfectly
aligned, a helical coupler is going to be
good for any shafts that have a little bit of angular
misalignment, but what if you have a parallel
offset? A parallel offset is where the two
shafts are like this, but there is a bit of
an offset between them. It's really difficult
to transfer the motion between these two shafts,
when they are offset like that. So the best way
to deal with it would be to use
some sort of gear, pulley or belt system
and we'll be talking about those in later videos.
Wheels are going to be the most common thing
people are going to attach to the end of
a motor, because it makes things drive,
it makes things move, and it's pretty cool.
I've got a few different types of wheels
here, and the first thing you'll notice is
the actual width of the tread, or the thing that
touches the ground. You've got a big wheel
here, this came off a wild thumper chassis, and
we've got one of these small wheels, which is
an Actobotics precision disk wheel.
Now, why would you use this one over
this one? The procession disk wheel is going
to have a much better time turning precisely
especially on a flat smooth surface,
where as something like this is going to take
a lot more force to turn on a flat surface.
This is not going to be turning handling type
wheel, where this is. That being said, the really
small profile of this wheel means that the
overall weight of the robot is being spread out
over a much smaller space, where as if you have
a very heavy robot sitting on this, the weight
is going to be spread out over a much larger
surface area, thus giving you little bit more
traction and also distribute the load a little
bit better. But why would you choose something
like a skate wheel, something like this,
or maybe a larger wheel like these heavy duty
wheels from Actobotics. These give you a little
bit of the best of both worlds. They have a
very narrow profile as you can see,
this one has a little bit more, but they are
also sturdy enough to handle a higher load.
Now something to take into consideration
with wheels is you have the RPM of the output
shaft but choosing two different sized wheels,
is going to change how fast the robot can go.
If we take the outer circumference of this
wheel, one revolution can go, let's say, this far,
but with this wheel however, it might be
like this far. So when designing a robot,
and designing the speed that you want it to go,
or even trying to decide the RPM of the motor,
you're going to have to consider the outer size
of the wheel or the overall circumference of
the wheel to determine how fast or how far
it can go per revolution. The basic concept
of angular motion is taking a motor and spinning
something else. Now in an ideal
world we have just a motor with some kind
of wheel spinning on the end of it. Now the problem
with that thinking is there's always going to be
some sort of load exerted on that wheel,
or on that thing that's attached so we're going
to need bearings. There are several different
types of barrings and they all serve a little bit
different purpose. But generally, a bearing
is there to make sure that the motor spins
smoothly and quietly. They take a lot of the load
that is exerted against the output shaft
of the motor. Some motors already have bearings
in them, for example the stepper motor has a
pretty big bearing on the output shaft
and it is good at taking loads against the side
so if you push against the side of the
shaft it can actually handle that pretty
well; however, most motors, do not have
a bearing on the output shaft, so you'll need
to provide one yourself. Join us next week
for the third video in the robotic series which
will be linear motion. Linear motion is a little
bit different from angular motion in that we
are interested in things moving in a linear
plane rather then a rotational plane.
So we'll see you again next week for
linear motion.
[Outro Music]