The core skills are icons which appear on all the
SparkFun product pages on our website.
They give you an idea of how hard a product is to use
or more importantly the barrier to entry for each one of the
different products. The categories are separated into five
different core skills. There's soldering, programming,
electrical prototyping, robotics, and DIY.
And each one of these five skills, have five different
skill levels. These five individual skills ranging from 1
the easiest, to 5 the most difficult give you an idea
of roughly how difficult something is, or the barrier to entry.
1 is defined as a Noob. This is someone that is
completely new to this idea or concept and has never had any
exposure to it. For instance someone with programming
a level 1 is someone that has never even done drag
and drop programming and they are very new to the concept
in general. Level 2 is a Rookie. A Rookie is
someone who has a little experience in this skill
but hasn't had any really formal training. In the example of programming
they might have done something with drag and drop
and they might know some of the basics of programming
but they are going to need a descent amount of hand holding
to get through the different examples.
Level 3 is Competent. This is someone who has some formal knowledge
and some fundamental skill. This differs
from level 1 and level 2 in that at level 3
you really do need to have some sort of fundamentals
behind you before tackling this skill.
Level 4 is Experienced. At this level you really need
to know what you are doing, and you need
have a lot of background knowledge. It is almost impossible
to start out at a level 4. You might be able to start at
level 3 with a lot of blood sweat and tears,
but a Level 4 is going to be nearly impossible.
Level 5 is Expert. At this level, most everything is
going to be completely up to you.
You're going to have to do your own research,
you're going to have to figure out everything by yourself,
and you are considered an expert in this skill.
The next thing we'd like to talk about
is assumed application. There are many products in
our catalog that can be used a lot of different
ways. They could be beginner for some but
you could also use them for much higher
applications. For our listing purposes, we choose
everything as the base barrier to entry,
based on the assumed application.
For instance, with an Arduino, we are putting
a level 2 with programming because, generally,
most things are relatively easy with the Arduino
but of course you can use it with a lot more
complex applications. To determine the overall
difficulty level, or the barrier to entry for an entire
project, all we need to do is look at each
individual part that will go into the project
and then we just take highest number from all
the different skills, and that will be the
total barrier to entry. So, let's say
we have a project involving a stepper motor.
The stepper motor itself might not require
programming, but either the Arduino or
the driver that is driving the stepper motor
might. So, if we take the core skills from each
one of the three different aspects, the Arduino,
the stepper motor driver, and the stepper motor
itself and combine them and just take
the highest number from all the different core
skills, that gives you an idea of the barrier
to entry for the entire project.
[Outro Music]